Mom and Dad sent me a video message on my computer.
なんばひびと
(南波日々人)母ちゃんたちから
ﾋﾞﾃﾞｵﾒｰﾙ来てんだよ｡
俺のパソコンに｡件名に
｢六太 ニ次試験結果報告｣➡
The subject is "Mutta's Second Exam Results."
って書いてあんだ｡
むった
ここでみんなと一緒に見る？
We could all watch it together here.
I'm Nanba Mutta, age thirty-two.
＜私 南波六太３２才は
きてん
持ち前の機転と実力で➡
Thanks to my wits and ability, I've passed the second round of JAXA's astronaut selection exam.
せんばつしけん
ＪＡＸＡの宇宙飛行士選抜試験
とっぱ
二次試験を無事突破＞
You have passed the second exam.
＜そしてついに
宇宙飛行士選抜 最後のとりで➡
And now,
it's finally time for the last test, the third exam.
三次試験が始まろうとしていた＞
Space Brothers
Ah
This feels so good, different from usual
I have no idea what's going on
It feels so good
I never understand what's going on around me
Nothing makes sense to me
Full of questions
Feel so moon
I danced with you in a desert lit by the moon
I won't lose to the rabbit and fly high
I'll fly high
#10 Running Bus
《まったく…今日から息子が
人生をかけた三次試験に➡
Seriously...
Your son is heading off to an exam that could completely change his life.
旅立つというのに…うん!?》
Snacks
《ケンジには
抱えているものがある｡➡
Kenji has responsibilities.
命をかけることになったら
その重さは倍増する》
That means he has to think twice
if he's asked to risk his life.
こころざし
《せりかさんには強い志がある｡➡
Serika has a strong sense of purpose.
やらなきゃいけない
大事な仕事がある》
She has a very important goal.
《で…俺には何かあったっけ？➡
And me?
Do I have any reason?
たいして何もないくせに
浮かれ過ぎだろ》
I shouldn't celebrate, when I have no reason.
ハァ ハァ…｡
あこが
《ただの憧れだけで
三次試験まで行ってしまって➡
I've made it to the third exam because becoming an astronaut was my dream.
いいんでしょうか？》
Is that really good enough?
That's fine.
(シャロン)いいのよ それで｡
やっぱり
そう言われると思ってた｡
I figured you'd say that.
Astronauts have many different roles to play.
宇宙飛行士になってからの役割は
そりゃあ 色々あるだろうけど➡
But most got started for similar reasons.
どうき
最初の動機なんて
みんな大差ないわよ｡➡
こうきしん
好奇心だったり憧れだったり｡➡
Whether they're driven by curiosity or inspiration,
入口は夢見る少年少女よ｡
ムッタと同じ｡➡
they were once boys and girls with a dream, just like you.
はい できた｡
Here, all done.
きっとその
せりかちゃんって子も➡
I'll bet that Serika girl
着メロはスター･ウォーズ
だったりするのよ｡
has a Star Wars ringtone.
《まさか》
No way...
悩むなら なってから悩みなさい｡
After you become an astronaut, you can find your reason.
大きい荷物ね｡
That's a big bag.
２週間泊り込みなんだって
三次試験は｡
For the third exam, they said we'll be out there two weeks.
じゃあ 行ってくるよ
シャロンおばちゃん｡
Well, I'm off, Aunt Sharon.
うん？どうしたの？
What is it?
ううん ちょっとね｡
考えてみただけ｡
Oh, I was just doing some thinking...
巣立つ我が子を見送る気持ちって
こんな感じなのかなって思って｡
This must be how sending off a child feels.
ホントだよ｡
No kidding.
You're acting more motherly than my own mom.
シャロンおばちゃんの方が
よっぽど母親らしいよ｡
今朝 家を出る時 ウチの母ちゃん
なんて ま～だ寝てたからね｡
When I left the house this morning, Mom was still asleep.
ウフフ…行ってらっしゃい｡
Take care.
行ってきま～す｡
I'm off!
It's been twenty years...
《あれから ２０年か…》
Oh? Who might you be?
⦅あら？どちら様？⦆
⦅あの…初めまして！➡
Uh, nice to meet you.
ぼうえんきょう
ここに望遠鏡があるって
聞いたんで 来ました⦆
We heard there was a telescope here, so we came.
やしき
うわさ
⦅違うよ｡オバケ屋敷って噂で…⦆
⦅だまれ 日々人⦆
What?
Everyone says this house is haunted...
Shut up, Hibito!
⦅あ あの ここで月見たら
こんな風に見えますか？⦆
Uh...
Would we be able to see the moon up close, like in this picture?
⦅うん？⦆
⦅どうぞ 入って⦆
Please come in.
I'm amazed that you walked through the forest to get here.
⦅よくこんな森の中 歩いて
来たわね｡怖くなかった？⦆
Were you scared?
ちょう
⦅もう 超～怖かったっス！⦆
⦅あれ？オバケ屋敷じゃないね⦆
It was super scary!
Huh? This isn't a haunted house?
After you become an astronaut, you can find your reason.
《悩むなら なってから
悩みなさい…か》
I'm glad I dropped by before heading to the third exam.
《三次試験の前に
立ち寄って良かった｡➡
シャロンはいつも
俺の頭をほぐしてくれる》
Sharon always helps me clear my head.
Third Exam
Orientation
(せりか)…私もなんです｡
(北村)よろしく｡
Same here...
It's a pleasure.
こちらこそ
よろしくお願いします｡
The pleasure is mine.
１３ １４ １５…
おい １５人もいるぞ！
Thirteen, fourteen, fifteen...
There are fifteen people here!
なんてこった 三次に残るのは
８人だと思ってたのに｡
What's going on?
I thought they only chose eight people for the third exam.
(ケンジ)僕もそう思ってた｡➡
That's what I thought, too.
前回 前々回が
８人だったらしいから｡
The last two times, there were only eight.
おまけに泊り込みで
一体何をするんだよ｡
And why are they keeping us here for two weeks?
にった
(新田)南波日々人の
お兄ちゃんか…｡
Nanba Hibito's older brother...
まかべ
南波さん 真壁さん｡
Nanba, Makabe.
Oh, Seri...
いとう
あ！せり…い 伊東さん｡
やあ｡
I-Itou.
Hey.
いよいよ 三次試験ですね｡
お互いがんばりましょう｡
It's finally time for the third exam.
Let's do our best.
は…はい～｡
Right.
S-Sure...
じゃあ また後で｡
Well, I'll see you later.
《どんな試験だろうと
せりかさんと一緒なら…いい》
It doesn't matter what the exam is like...
If I get to be with Serika,
it's fine.
始まるみたいだよ ムッ君｡
Looks like they're starting, Mu.
つるみ
え～ みなさん お忙しい中➡
Well, I would like to thank everyone for making room in their busy schedules to participate in the third exam.
この三次試験にお集まり頂き
ありがとうございます｡➡
今回は この１５名の中から数名が
宇宙飛行士として選ばれます｡
This time, we will be choosing a few astronauts
from the fifteen people here.
《あ!?なんだ？
どこかで見たような…》
Huh?
What?
He looks familiar...
Next, we will have a brief introduction
あいさつ
(鶴見)それでは 開会の挨拶を➡
なすだ
茄子田理事長にして頂きます｡
from Director Nasuda.
Oh!
⦅Did you find something new
about yourself,recently?⦆
Did you find something new about yourself recently?
《あ あれが理事長だったのか》
Th-That was the director?
オッホン！え～ みなさん
ようこそＪＡＸＡへ｡
So I would like to welcome everyone to JAXA.
私が噂の茄子田です｡
え～ じゃあまぁ 早速ね➡
As you've heard, I am Nasuda.
Then let us get started with the third exam!
あの 三次試験
始めちゃいましょう！
(ケンジ)今から？
Now?
あ スタートォー!!
Start!
ふるや
(古谷)なにをやねん
What was that about?
(職員)あ～ じゃあ みなさん｡
これから移動しますので➡
Okay, everyone!
We'll be leaving now,
外のバスに乗ってくださ～い｡
so please board the bus outside!
てしま
(手島)移動？
もりしま
(森嶋)どこへ行くんだ？
Leaving?
Where are we going?
ふくだ
なんだ ここでやらないのか？
Isn't the exam taking place here?
長旅だからね｡
トイレには行っといれ｡
It will be a long trip.
Use the restroom while you can.
いやぁ～ケンジ
バスに乗るとは思わなかったな｡
So, Kenji...
I hadn't planned on a bus ride.
良かった～
俺 お菓子持って来て｡
Good thing I brought snacks.
(係官)は～い 乗って下さ～い｡
Okay, please board the bus!
なんか遠足気分でいいね
ケンジ君｡
It almost feels like a field trip, huh?
ムッ君 そうでもなさそうだよ｡
No, Mu.
That doesn't seem to be the case.
うわぁ～｡
え…あっ！
なんだよ このバス!?
What's with this bus?
(鶴見)では 乗車して頂きます｡
Everyone, please board.
(鶴見)大きな荷物はトランクに➡
Please stow any large luggage below.
けいたい
携帯電話や時計は
こちらにお預け下さい｡
Leave cell phones and watches at the front.
気持ち悪っ｡
景色など見るなと｡➡
This is creepy.
They don't want us to see the scenery.
ごくひ
行先は極秘ってやつかな｡
I guess we're going somewhere top-secret...
なんか 怖いね｡
This is a little scary.
なぁ ムッ君 気付いた？
Hey, Mu, did you notice?
しゅんかん
ん？…ああ 乗った瞬間に
ピンと来たよ｡
Hmm?
Yeah...
It hit me the second I stepped on board.
そうか さすがムッ君｡
I see.
You're as sharp as always.
《まさか ＪＡＸＡの試験が
ここまでとは…➡
I wasn't expecting a JAXA exam like this.
このバスは全席…
かんし
カメラで監視されている！》
Every seat is monitored by cameras.
《間違いないぜ
このバスの運転手は…➡
I know what's going on.
The bus driver
ヅラだ！》
is bald!
Well, it shouldn't be an issue.
まぁ別に
大した問題じゃねえけど｡
きもすわ
そぉ!?肝座ってるなぁ～ ムッ君｡
Really?
You're pretty calm...
Okay, everyone is now on board.
(鶴見)さて 全員揃いましたね｡
それでは 出発します｡
Then we'll depart.
これで 全く景色が
見れない状態だ｡
We won't be able to see anything outside.
《そうか 分かったぞ》
Oh, I've figured it out...
《せ～りかさん》
Serika...
⦅あ スタートォー!!⦆
Start!
《あの時から
もう 試験は始まってるんだ》
That was when
the third exam began.
《みんなは気付いてんのかな
監視カメラに…》
Has anyone else noticed the cameras?
(ケンジ)《このバスで 僕らの何を
見ようってんだ…》
What are they trying to monitor on this bus?
あの スミマセン｡
到着は何時頃ですか？➡
Um, excuse me.
When will we reach our destination?
行き先も
まだ聞いてませんけど｡
We haven't been told where we're going.
答えられません｡
I cannot tell you.
このバスを見れば
お分かりでしょう｡
When you saw the bus, you should have realized.
これから向かう試験場は 特別な
場所に設けられた極秘施設です｡➡
We're en route to a top-secret facility.
時間･方角など 場所を特定できる
情報は 一切教えられません｡➡
We cannot provide any information that would compromise its location.
出発前に皆さんから 携帯や時計を
回収したのは そのためです｡
That is why we asked
that everyone turn in their cell phones and watches earlier.
(溝口)《場所なんて
どこだっていいだろ》
Who cares where this place is?
《そこまでする必要があるって事は
とんでもない施設だな…》
The facility must be really special if they're being this careful.
ふあぁ…｡
おい～ いつまで乗んねん
このバス｡長過ぎやろ｡
Hey, how long will we be on this bus?
This is taking forever.
I wouldn't know.
俺に聞かれても｡まだ
１時間くらいしか経ってないよ｡
And it's only been an hour.
おい 手島｡ビンボーゆすり
やめろや｡振動が来んねん｡
Hey, Teshima...
Stop jerking your leg.
It's annoying.
いらだ
《その苛立ち…
見られてるし 聴かれてるぞ》
Your tantrum has just been witnessed
《監視カメラの向こうにいる
試験官の連中に…！》
by the judges behind the cameras.
(鶴見)え～皆さん｡それじゃあ➡
Now, everyone...
We will begin with an icebreaker.
ここらへんで
｢交流会｣といきましょう｡
ここに 席の番号が書かれた
くじびきがあります｡➡
This is a box containing seat numbers.
１人ずつ これを引いて
出た番号の席に移動して下さい｡➡
I need each person to draw one, then take the designated seat.
そこで隣り合った人と１０分間
きっちり話をしてもらいます｡➡
You will spend ten minutes
talking to the person next to you.
１人余りますので その人は
１０分間 待ってもらいます｡
We have an odd number,
so one person will need to wait ten minutes.
Put me next to Serika! Put me next to Serika!
《せりかさんの隣 せりかさんの隣
せりかさんの隣～っ!!》
Put me next to Serika...
ムッ君 くじ来てるよ｡
Mu, it's your turn.
これだ!!
There!
さあ 全員 引いた席に
着きましたね｡
Now, could everyone move to their designated seat?
それでは…始めて下さい｡
And begin...
Now.
よろしく よろしく 南波六太君｡
Nice to meet you, Nanba Mutta.
あ…どうも よろしくです｡
Oh, yeah...
Nice meeting you.
あの…俺のこと
知ってるんですか？
Uh, do you know me?
そりゃ知ってるよ～｡
有名人だもん 君｡
Sure I do.
You're famous.
僕は 森嶋茂雄 ４０歳｡
Morishima Shigeo (40)
I'm Morishima Shigeo, forty years old.
あの長嶋茂雄と一文字違いだ｡
Nagashima Shigeo
My name is one character different than Nagashima Shigeo.
Morishima Shigeo (40)
Nagashima Shigeo
That's why I'm a Giants fan.
だから 巨人ファンなんだよ｡
なるほど～｡
Oh, I see...
(森嶋)昔はよく あの中田ヒデに
似てるって…➡
People used to tell me that I looked like Nakata Hide.
言われたことはないが
自分では そう思っていたよ｡
なるほど～｡
Well, no one ever said it.
But I always thought I did.
Really...
(森嶋)僕の飼ってる犬はね
どことなく➡
My pet dog kind of looks like Tom Cruise.
トム･クルーズに似てるんだよね｡
だからトムって名づけたんだ｡
So I named him Tom.
この前 トムを連れて
東京湾クルーズに行ってね…｡
A while back, I took him on a Tokyo Bay cruise, and then he really was Tom Cruise.
《これ１０分はキツいな…》
Ten minutes of this will be torture.
え？お刺身にワインですか？
What?
Sashimi with wine?
ええ シャブリという
辛口の白ワインは…｡
Yes, there's this wine called a Chablis...
(清水)私も それ見たよ｡
I saw that.
(増田)そうですか
それなら話が早い｡
でも 意外ですね～｡
Really? Then that makes this easier.
But it was quite a surprise.
Man...
あ～あ ほんま
ついてへんわ 俺っ！
I'm so unlucky.
なんで またお前やねん｡
Why am I next to you again?
だから やめろって
ビンボーゆすり｡
Would you stop jerking your leg?
まだ ペアになれただけ
マシだよ｡
You should be glad to be paired with someone.
あそこの彼女みたいに
１人の方が ついてない｡
Ending up alone like her would've been worse.
Why am I the only one who's alone?
《なんで私だけ こんな席に
なっちゃったんだろ…ヒマだ》
I'm so bored...
１人の方が ついてないって➡
You really think it'd be worse to end up alone, Teshima?
ほんまに
そう思ってんのか？手島｡
そうか 君にも娘がいるのか｡
Oh, you have a daughter, too?
２才っていうと かわいいけど
手のかかる時期だな｡
Two-year-olds are adorable, but they can be quite a handful.
本当にそうですよ｡福田さんも
娘さんが いらっしゃるんですか？
You're absolutely right.
So you have a daughter?
Hmm? Yes, I do.
ん…ああ 私にもいるよ｡
今はもう…２３かな｡
I think she's twenty-three now.
こんなこと言うと
年がバレちゃうかな｡
Well, now you know my age.
アハハ…｡
(ケンジ)《５４！》
Fifty-four!
５４なんだ｡
《よし！当たった!!》
I'm fifty-four.
Yes! I was right!
今回の候補者の中じゃ
最高齢らしい｡
I believe I'm the oldest applicant here.
《５４か…すごいな》
Fifty-four...
Impressive.
髪を といたことは？
Have you ever brushed her hair?
Huh?
(福田)娘さんの髪
といたことはある？
Have you ever brushed your daughter's hair?
(ケンジ)あ…ええ ２～３回｡
Oh, yes...
Two or three times.
そうか…たまにでも
といてあげた方がいい｡
I see...
I'd recommend you brush her hair every now and then.
(古谷)お前 あのツルツルの
おっちゃんの話➡
You weren't listening to that bald guy, were you?
あんま聞いてなかったやろ｡
何て言うてはった｡
What did he say?
何って…｡
はなし
｢10分間きっちり話して下さい｣や｡
You're asking me?
"Spend ten minutes talking."
That means we have to talk the whole time.
｢きっちり10分間｣と ちゃうぞ｡
｢10分間きっちり｣や｡
要するに お前と10分間も
しゃべり続けなあかんねんて｡
So you and I have to chat for ten minutes,
話題もないのに｡
そ そんな～｡
even though we have nothing to discuss.
N-Nah...
深読みしすぎだって
やっさん｡
You're being overly cautious.
浅読みしてドツボに
ハマるよりマシやろ｡➡
I'd rather avoid a careless mistake that ruins my chances.
注意深く 用心深く 念には念を｡➡
Be careful, cautious, and ever vigilant.
それが宇宙飛行士として
必要な資質ってこと➡
What if they expect their astronauts to demonstrate those qualities?
試されてたら どうする？
後ろの２人 見てみ 手島｡
さっきから会話 止まっとるやろ｡➡
Look at the pair behind us.
They've stopped talking.
あんな風に無言の状態が
続いたらやな 減点の対象や｡
I bet that'll cost them points.
ただの交流会だよ これ｡
減点とかはないでしょ｡
But this is only an icebreaker.
They aren't judging us yet.
おいおい ただの交流会で
監視カメラが必要か？
Please...
Would they need cameras for a normal icebreaker?
か 監視カメラ!?
C-Cameras?
やめとけ！
10分間 しゃべっとけば➡
Stop that.
We just have to talk for ten minutes,
ええんやから
しりとりでもしとこか｡
so let's play a word game or something.
それでは 10分経ったので➡
Ten minutes have passed.
通路側の人は 時計回りに
１つ席を移動して下さい｡➡
Would the people in aisle seats please move clockwise?
これを繰り返して１周したら➡
Once this is done, we will give you further instructions.
次の移動は
こちらから指示します｡
なんだ 結局みんなと話すのか｡
Oh, so we get to talk to everyone?
だったら 最初のくじは
何だったんだい｡
What was the point in drawing names?
合計140分も
しゃべり続けなあかんのか…｡
We have to spend a hundred and forty minutes talking?
シャレならんな｡
やっさんは得意だろ｡
That's no fun.
You shouldn't have any trouble.
《フッフッフッフッ…
そうか 全員と話すのか…》
Oh... So we get to talk with everyone.
《なら いつか必ず せりかさんと
話せるってことじゃないか！》
That means I'll be able to talk with Serika!
今 ジブン 俺の顔見て
｢目ぇ小っちゃ！｣って思ったやろ｡
You just looked at me and thought that my eyes are small, right?
いや 思ってないよ
何言ってんだよ｡
No, I didn't.
What are you talking about?
ほんまか？
《なんで
こんな奴が残ってんだ？》
Really?
How did this guy pass?
でも｢なんで こんな奴が三次まで
残ってんねん｣的な事は思たやろ？
But you were wondering how I made it to the third exam, right?
《思った！》
Of course not.
You bet I was!
え 好きな食べ物ですか？
Oh, my favorite foods?
洋食も和食も好き！
Hmm...
I like Chinese...
And I like Western and Japanese food.
I also like French, Italian, and Spanish.
あとは フレンチにイタリアン
スペイン料理とかも…｡
(鶴見)さて 交流会は以上です｡
お疲れ様でした｡
Okay, that ends the icebreaker.
Good work.
さすがに ２時間半
話し続けるのは つらいね｡
まあなぁ でも…｡
It was pretty hard to keep talking for two and a half hours.
Yeah, but...
《あ～あ せりかさんとの
とろける10分間は➡
The ten minutes I spent with Serika felt more like two.
まるで２分にしか
感じなかった…》
⦅映画とか 何がお好きですか？⦆
Are there any particular movies you like?
⦅｢スペースカウボーイ｣とか
｢アルマゲドン｣とか➡
I loved Space Cowboys,
Armageddon, and Star Wars.
｢スター･ウォーズ｣も好きですね⦆
Actually, I have a Star Wars ringtone.
⦅着メロも スター･ウォーズに
してるくらいなんです⦆
What?
⦅え～！僕も スター･ウォーズ
大好きです⦆
I've always been a Star Wars fan.
《あとで着メロ
スター･ウォーズに変えよっと》
I need to get a Star Wars ringtone.
それでは これから
アンケート用紙を配りますので➡
Next, I will be passing out a survey.
各自 記入して下さい｡➡
Please fill it out.
１枚目は この１５名の名簿で
写真と名前が書いてあります｡➡
The first sheet has the names and pictures
Astronaut Selection Exam Third Exam Roster
of the fifteen remaining applicants.
もう１枚には
１～１５までの記入欄があります｡
Astronaut Selection Exam
Third Exam Ranking
Name
The second sheet has lines numbered from one through fifteen.
１～１５？
One through fifteen?
Huh?
(鶴見)もう おわかりでしょう｡
I'm sure you've figured it out.
自分も含め 宇宙飛行士に
向いていると感じた人の➡
I want you to rank each person, including yourself, by their qualification to be an astronaut.
優先順位をつけて下さい｡
そんな…｡
Really?
そう来たか～｡
マ マジかよ…｡
So that's what this is about.
S-Seriously?
だから それ やめ～って！
あ ごめん｡
Could you stop that?
Oh, sorry.
《おなかすいた～
もう限界かも…》
I'm hungry.
I can't take this any more...
これから 食事の時間とします｡
Next, we will start serving meals.
きたっ!!
There we go!
大盛りだって｡やった!!
いただきま～す｡
A large serving...
Yay!
Thank you!
いただきます｡
Thank you...
That was delicious.
《おいしかった～》
ごちそうさまでした｡
Thanks for the meal.
《まあ 大盛りってほどじゃ
なかったけど…》
Well, it wasn't that large of a serving.
We will now be turning off the lights.
では 消灯時間とします｡➡
到着次第 皆さんには
次の試験に入っていただきます｡
Once we arrive, you will begin the next exam.
今のうちに お休みしておくことを
おすすめします｡では｡
I recommend that you get some rest.
Well, then...
＜私達が眠りについた後も
バスは走り続けた＞
After we fell asleep, the bus continued to run.
＜一体 何時間ぐらい
経ったのだろうか？＞
How many hours has it been?
＜目が覚めた時
バスは止まっていた＞
When I woke up,
the bus had already stopped.
The stars I admired were too bright for me
so I quietly closed my eyes
I have faith in you, as you stand alone, full of doubts
I'm right here, next to you
Come now, take my hand and hold it tight
If you do, we will always
have hope, shine with light
and overcome whatever we might face
Do you see how wonderful this world is
and how our future unfolds?
Even the tears we shed and could not put into words
will one day dry up, I am sure
One by one the smiles spread
and ascend towards the starlit sky
＜宇宙飛行士を選ぶ三次試験＞
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#11 Trapped Rivals
The third astronaut selection exam!
＜謎の会場に たどりついた
俺たちは 閉鎖環境の中で➡
After arriving at a strange facility,
they say we have to spend the next two weeks here.
課題をこなしながら
２週間過ごすことに＞
＜フフフ…私は せりかさんと
同じ班になりました＞
I was assigned to Serika's team!
Nanba, we're supposed to determine who's most qualified to be an astronaut...
＜南波さん 自分たちで➡
宇宙飛行士に ふさわしい人を
選ぶんですって＞
＜フフ フフ…えっ え～!?＞
Wh-What?
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Trapped Rivals".
＜閉鎖環境って…
ご飯 あるよね？＞
They'll feed us
while we're locked up here, right?!
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
今週の
宇宙写真です！
スッゲー！
Awesome!